A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 8520 emails.
  - Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries O. Nick Surace Email, 2008-2009.
    The subseries contains 28 email messages in one PST file: NSURACE.PST. Nick Surace served as a Governor's Fellow (Summer 2007) and Director of Gubernatorial Appointments from August 2007 to January 2010. He assisted the Governor and Secretary of the Commonwealth in searching for well-qualified citizens to server on 120 boards and commissions in the areas of education, natural resources, finance and administration. Surace was also responsible for tracking General Assembly legislation that may affect the operations of the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth. The date range of the email in this subseries is January 2008 to March 2009.
    Subjects include: General Assembly legislation related to the operations of the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
    Correspondents include: Bernie Henderson, Gary Janak, Jennie Moline, Megan Root, and Brian Shepard.
  - Series IV. Secretary of the Commonwealth Electronic Files, Subseries P. Dawn Farrar Email, 2006-2007.
    The subseries contains 382 email messages in one PST file: DFARRAR.PST. Farrar served as Deputy Secretary of the Commonwealth from January 2006 to June 2007.
    DFARRAR.PST contains 382 emails sent and received by Dawn Farrar between January 2006 and March 2007.
    Subjects include: board profiles; legislation; and weekly reports.
    Correspondents include: Kathryn Defilippo, Kate Hanley, Bernard Henderson, Bill Leighty, Joanna Martin, Bill Murray, Svandis Pollard, Brian Shepard, Wayne Turnage, and Jonathan Young.
- Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, 2005-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 15701 emails.
  The Secretary of Technology Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration. This series contains 15701 emails in seven (7) subseries. Subseries have been designated for A. Aneesh Chopra Email; B. Tristen Pegram Email; C. Len Pomata Email; D. John McDonald Email; E. Tim Bass Email, 2005-2006; F. Karen Jackson Email; and G. Brian Chiglinsky Email. There are 320 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel information.
  The Secretary of Technology and its agencies are responsible for the efficient and effective use of information technology to simplify government operations, advance technology applications to improve public services, and drive the innovation economy through the Commonwealth's leadership. The Secretary of Technology oversees two agencies: Virginia's Center for Innovative Technology (CIT) and the Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA).
  On 15 December 2005, Governor-elect Tim Kaine appointed Aneesh Chopra as Secretary of the Commonwealth. Prior to joining Governor Kaine's cabinet, Chopra served as Managing Director with the Advisory Board Company, a publicly-traded health care think tank serving nearly 2,500 hospitals and health systems. He led the firm's Financial Leadership Council and the Working Council for Health Plan Executives, as well as assisted the launch of the firm's first business intelligence software solution, Compass. Chopra left the administration in April 2009 when he was named the United States' first Chief Technology Officer by President Barack Obama. In June 2009, Governor Kaine appoint Len Pomata Secretary of Technology; he served until the end of the administration.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries A. Aneesh Chopra Email, 2006-2009.
    The subseries contains 195 email messages in one PST file: KaineLibachopra.pst. Aneesh Chopra served as Secretary of Technology from 2006 to April 2009. There are 10 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information. Additional Chopra email is contained in his assistant's, Tristen Pegram, email.
    Subjects include: telework, Office of Health IT, technology in education, and broadband stimulus.
    Notable email includes: email exchange between Chopra, Governor Kaine, and John Knapp of Verizon, dated 15 March 2009, regarding broadband stimulus.
    Correspondents include: Peter Blake, Amir Huddan, Tim Kaine, Bill Leighty, L. Scott Lingamfelter, Joe May, and Judy Napier.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries B. Tristen Pegram, 2006-2009.
    The subseries contains 7072 email messages in one PST file: Kainelibtpegram.pst. Tristen Pegram, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Technology, served from 2006 until 13 November 2009. After leaving the Secretary of Technology's office, she served in the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy and then on the campaign team for Aneesh Chopra's 2013 unsuccessful bid for Lieutenant Governor of Virginia. A large portion of this PST file seems to be the correspondence of Aneesh Chopra, Secretary of Technology from 2006 to 2009. There are 80 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: the legislative and policy priorities of the Secretariat of Technology; grants given by the Center for Innovative Technology, the Productivity Investment Fund, and the Commonwealth Technology Research Fund; the Commonwealth of Virginia Innovative Technology Symposium; health information technology and electronic medical records; improvements to broadband access for rural populations; and the implementation of the public-private partnership between the Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman.
    Correspondents include: Preston Bryant, Aneesh Chopra, Thomas Gates, Karen Jackson, Peter Jobse, and Marilyn Tavenner.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries C. Len Pomata Email, 2009-2010.
    The subseries contains 570 email messages in one PST file: LPOMATA.PST. Len Pomata served as the Secretary of Technology from 5 June 2009 until the end of the administration in January 2010. He also served as interim Chief Information Officer after the firing of Lem Stewart from 12 June 2009 until 20 August 2009. There are 29 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: VITA/Northrop Grumman partnership; VITA management and budget issues; the Virginia Information Technology Investment Board (ITIB); the Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), the planning for the 2009 COVITS conference, and health information technology.
    Notable email includes: email, dated 9 August 2009, about the structure of the Commonwealth's deal with CGI-AMS and two emails, dated 11 August 2009, with Hiram Johnson about the relationship between Pomata and the ITIB.
    Correspondents include: Brian Chiglinsky, John McDonald, Tristen Pegram, Marilyn Tavenner, and Wayne Turnage.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries D. John McDonald Email, 2009-2010.
    The subseries contains 2783 email messages in two PST files: JMCDONALD.PST and KaineLibjmcdonald.pst. John McDonald served as Deputy Secretary of Technology from March 2009 to July 2010. There are 24 privacy protected and confidential emails in these PST files that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    The JMCDONALD.PST contains 2302 emails sent by John McDonald between 2009 and 2010. The KaineLibjmcdonald.pst contains 481 emails received by John McDonald between 2009 and 2010.
    Subjects include: management of and issues with the Commonwealth of Virginia's contract with Northrop Grumman for their information technology infrastructure, including the re-negotiation and re-baselining of the contract. There is also information about the planning of the 2009 COVITS conference as well as the transition from the Tim Kaine administration to the Robert McDonnell administration.
    Notable email includes: email from Wayne Turnage, dated 8 April 2009, about the issues with the Northrup Grumman contract; email from Aneesh Chopra, dated 21 April 2009, discussing the issues between VITA and Northrup Grumman; email dated 11 June 2009 about Lem Stewart being removed as Virginia's Chief Information Officer (CIO); email from Jackie Simien-Jones, dated 29 July 2009, containing a letter from Fred Duball to Northrop Grumman withholding payment due to alleged violations of the contract; email to Len Pomata, dated 4 August 2009, about issues between VITA and Northrop Grumman; and email to George Coulter, dated 8 September 2009, regarding a proposal for a new contract with Northrop Grumman.
    Correspondents include: Fred Duball, Cynthia Cordova-Edwards, Len Pomata, David Swynford, and Wayne Turnage.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries E. Tim Bass Email, 2005-2006.
    The subseries contains 3576 email messages in one PST file: TBassKaine.pst. J. Timothy Bass served as Enterprise Applications Program Director from 11 April 2005 to 2006, as Deputy Secretary of Technology and Enterprise Applications Program Director from January to 1 July 2006, and as Enterprise Applications Program Director from 1 July 2006 to 2007. His work primarily concerned enterprise applications and their use by the Commonwealth of Virginia. Prior to his appointment, Bass worked for the Virginia Retirement System. There are 176 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: negotiations for the Enterprise Applications PPEA contract, for which there were two bids: CGI-AMS, who eventually was awarded the contract, and IBM/BearingPoint. The negotiations also included a number of outside consultants, including McClain Group II, Gordon and Glickson, Gartner Consulting, and Latham and Watkins. Also included are the due diligence for the project, the receipt of bids, the negotiations, and the reaction of the General Assembly.
    Notable email includes: email dated 7 September 2005 regarding the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) investigation of BearingPoint; email to Bill Leighty, dated 14 September 2005, regarding the vote to continue negotiations with CGI-AMS only; email from Lem Stewart, dated 25 October 2005, announcing the selection of Northrop Grumman as the IT infrastructure partner; email from Michael Hepburn, dated 16 December 2005, containing the final agreement between the Commonwealth of Virginia and CGI-AMS; and email from David Von Moll, dated 20 February 2006, regarding cuts to EA budget.
    Correspondents include: Paul Doty, Michael Hepburn, Daniel Keene, Bill Leighty, Carrie Nee, and John Westrick.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries F. Karen Jackson Email, 2008.
    The subseries contains 1 email message in one PST file: KJACKSON.pst. Karen Jackson served as the director of Office of Telework and Broadband Assistance. Jackson was appointed Deputy Secretary of Technology by Governor Kaine on 7 May 2009. The email is from 2008 between Jackson and State Senator Frank Ruff and the subject is the auction of the 700 mhz wireless band by the Federal Communications Commission.
  - Series V. Secretary of Technology Electronic Files, Subseries G. Brian Chiglinsky Email, 2008-2010.
    The subseries contains 1504 email messages in one PST file: KaineLibbchiglinsky.pst. Brian Chiglinsky served as a Governor's Fellow assigned to the Secretariat of Technology from 2 June 2008 until August 2008, the Special Assistant for Constituent Services from August 2008 to 10 June 2009, and then the Special Assistant to the Secretary of Technology from 11 June 2009 until the end of the administration. While working in Constituent Services, Chiglinsky continued to work on projects for the Secretary of Technology and also worked in the Executive Office of the Governor. There is 1 privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: creation, funding, organization, and operation of VA STAR, a program which takes used computers from a variety of donors and gives them to school districts throughout the Commonwealth. There is also correspondence relating to comments on the Governor's weekly reports and health care technology.
    Notable email includes: email from Andrew LeVasseur, dated 24 November 2009, which includes the award of over $300,000 from the Productivity Investment Fund to fund the VA STAR program.
    Correspondents include: Amber Amato, Aneesh Chopra, Chuck Drake, Sherrie Harrington, John McDonald, Tristen Pegram, and Len Pomata.
- Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 6774 emails.
  The Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the office during the Kaine Administration. This series contains 6774 emails in eleven (11) subseries. Subseries have been designated for A. John Marshall Email; B. Clyde Cristman Email; C. Marilyn Harris Email; D. Dawn Smith Email; E. Erin Bryant Email; F. Susan Gholson Email; G. Jacklyn Varela Email; H. Iva Frizzle Email; I. Martha Hazelgrove Email; J. Gabrielle Williams Email; and K. Beth Camphouse Email. There are 29 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800, 42.1-78 and 53.1-40.10. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: records containing personal/personnel and social services information.
  During the administration of Governor Timothy Kaine, the Secretary Public Safety provided guidance to the following state agencies: Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC), Commonwealth's Attorneys' Services Council (CAS); Department of Correctional Education (DCE), Department of Correction (DOC), Department of Criminal Justice Services (DCJS), Department of Emergency Management, Department of Fire Programs, Department of Forensic Science (DFS), Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP), Department of Juvenile Justice (DJJ), Department of Military Affairs (DMA), Virginia Parole Board, Virginia State Police (VSP), Department of Veterans Services (VDVA), and the Virginia War Memorial.
  These agencies enforced criminal, highway safety, and alcoholic beverage and tobacco laws; protected public safety through confinement, treatment and monitoring of felons and through the supervision, treatment and monitoring of people on parole or probation; provided technical assistance, research and training for law enforcement agencies, community fire departments and prosecutors; planed and coordinated the state's emergency preparedness, response, recovery and mitigation efforts; trained fire fighters, investigated crimes and tested crime scene evidence; trained Army and Air National Guard members; and provided services to Virginia's veterans.
  John Marshall served as Secretary of Public Safety from January 2002 to January 2010. Marshall was initially appointed by Governor Mark Warner in January 2002 and reappointed by Governor Tim Kaine on 15 January 2006.
  Marshall began his career in public service and law enforcement in 1980 as a Virginia State Trooper. During his 14 years with the Department of State Police, he also served as a Special Agent in the Narcotics Division, Sergeant-Instructor at the Training Academy and as a Sergeant assigned to Field Operations.
  In 1994, President William J. Clinton appointed Marshall to serve as the United States Marshal for the Eastern District of Virginia. Later in 1999, President Clinton nominated Marshall to serve as the Director of the United States Marshals Service, our nation's oldest federal law enforcement agency. Upon confirmation by the U.S. Senate, Marshall took office as Director in November of 1999. He is the first African-American to serve as the Director.
  Secretary Marshall graduated from Georgetown University in 1988 with a BA in Government, and he also holds a Post-Baccalaureate Certificate in the Administration of Justice from Virginia Commonwealth University.
  - Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries A. John Marshall Email, 2006-2009.
    The subseries contains 652 email messages in one PST file: KaineLibjmarshall.pst. John Marshall served as Secretary of Public Safety from 2002 to 2010. There are four privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 32.1-127.1:03, 42.1-78, and 63.2-103. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information.
    Subjects include: Virginia National Guard; Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC) take home vehicles; storm updates and damage assessments; declarations of state of emergencies; budget reductions; Department of Corrections' media interview policy; technology issues related to the Virginia Information Technologies Agency and Northrop Grumman (VITA/NG) contract; Virginia Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS); Virginia Tourism poster (gang sign); Virginia Citizen Soldier Support Council; 2009 presidential inaugural planning; Public Safety Memorial Commission; Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWAM) procurement program; 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; and the 2007 Governor's Campus Security Conference.
    Correspondents include: Vince Burgess, Michael Cline, Clyde Cristman, Robert Crouch, Pamela O'Berry Evans, W. Steven Flaherty, Marc Follmer, Stephen Harms, Marilyn Harris, Martha Hazelgrove, Pierce Homer, Tim Kaine, Robert Kemmler, Bill Leighty, John McDonald, Walter McFarlane, Robert Newman, Len Pomata, Larry Roberts, Mark Rubin, Brian Shepard, Delacey Skinner, Marilyn Tavenner, and Wayne Turnage.
  - Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries B. Clyde Cristman, 2006-2007.
    The subseries contains 804 email messages in one PST file: CCristman_SOPS.pst. Clyde Cristman served as Deputy Secretary of Public Safety from January 2006 to October 2007. Cristman left the Secretary of Public Safety's office for a position with the Virginia State Senate Finance Committee. There are four privacy protected and confidential emails in this PST file that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3800 and 42.1-78. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to personal/personnel information and medical information.
    Subjects include: Commonwealth Interoperability Coordinator's Office (CICO); State Interoperability Advisory Group; Criminal Justice Task Force of the Chief Justice's Commission on Mental Health Law Reform; 16 April 2007 shooting at Virginia Tech; DNA testing by the Virginia Department of Forensic Science (ordered by Governor Mark Warner in 2004); Virginia correctional system; prisoner re-entry; strategic plan for Secretary of Public Safety; and memorandum of understandings between Public Safety state agencies and Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA).
    Correspondents include: Robert Crouch, Chris Essid, Paul Ferrara, Iva Frizzell, Marilyn Harris, Jennifer Hastings, Martha Hazelgrove, Pete Marone, John Marshall, Melissa McMenemy, Kevin Patrick, Thomas Stuzzieri, Larry Traylor, Wayne Turnage, Carol Ulrich, and Charles Werner.
  - Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries C. Marilyn Harris Email, 2008-2010.
    The subseries contains 270 email messages in one PST file: MHARRIS.PST. Marilyn Harris served as Deputy Secretary of Public Safety and Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention (GOSAP) Director from January 2006 to January 2010. One email in this subseries is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 2.2-3801 and 42.1-78.
    Subjects include: budget reductions; public safety employee assistance; closure of Natural Bridge Juvenile Correctional Center (NBJCC); public safety legislation; electronic interrogations; and the Virginia Public Safety Memorial.
    Correspondents include: Helen Fahey, Pete Marone, Walter McFarlane, and B.J. Northington.
  - Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries D. Dawn Smith Email, 2002-2008.
    The subseries contains 603 email messages in one PST file: DSmith.pst. Dawn B. Smith served as Assistant Secretary of Public Safety from 2002 to 2006 in Governor Mark Warner's administration. She was reappointed by Governor Tim Kaine and served until August 2008. Smith also served as staff to the Virginia Citizen-Soldier Support Council, formed by Governor Mark Warner in 2003. Two emails are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 2.2-3801 and 42.1-78.
    Subjects include: Small, Women-owned, and Minority-owned Business (SWaM) and minority procurement; National Advisory Board, Norfolk State University Intelligence Community, Center for Academic Excellence (NSU ICCAE); reports to the Virginia General Assembly; Congressional briefings on public safety federal appropriation requests; and prisoner reentry.
    Correspondents include: Clyde Cristman, Barbara Lee, John Marshall, and Cindy Sanger.
  - Series VI. Secretary of Public Safety Electronic Files, Subseries E. Erin Bryant Email, 2005-2010.
    The subseries contains 2688 email messages in two PST files: KaineLibEBryant.pst and EBRYANT.PST. Erin Bryant served as Senior Special Assistant (2005-2008) and Assistant Secretary of Public Safety (2008-2010). In 2007, Bryant worked in the Office of Special Projects assisting with Queen Elizabeth II's visit to Virginia in May 2007. There are nine privacy protected and confidential emails in these PST files that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78 and 52-48. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to attorney-client privilege and Virginia Fusion Intelligence Center reports.
    The KaineLibEBryant.pst contains 2682 emails sent/received by Erin Bryant between August 2005 and January 2010. The EBRYANT.PST contains six emails sent/received by Erin Bryant on 15 January 2010.